ILGWU. Convention records, 5780/080
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Convention records
1977-1992.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/080
3 cubic feet
3 linear feet
Transcripts, notes.
Contains cue cards and transcripts of the conventions of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
5492766
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
March 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, March 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
"Permanent deposit"
Scope and Contents
Contains cue cards and transcripts of the conventions of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU Records
5780/072. ILGWU. Constitutions and dues books
5780/080mf. ILGWU. Convention records. Microfilm
5780/193 PUBS. ILGWU. Convention publications
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States
5492766
- 36th Convention, [Morning Session]. May 27, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 36th Convention, Afternoon Session. May 27, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 36th Convention, [Morning Session]. May 30, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 36th Convention, Afternoon Session. May 30, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 36th Convention, Morning Session. May 31, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 36th Convention, Afternoon Session. May 31, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 36th Convention, Morning Session. June 1, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 36th Convention, Afternoon Session. June 1, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 36th Convention, Morning Session, June 2, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 36th Convention, Afternoon Session. June 2, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 36th Convention. June 3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 37th Convention. Sunday, September 28, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 37th Convention, Monday, September 29, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 37th Convention. Tuesday, September 30, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 37th Convention. Wednesday, October 1, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 37th Convention. Thursday, October 2, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 37th Convention. Friday, October 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 38th Convention. Monday, May 30, 1983. Day 2. Pages 171-329 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 38th Convention. Monday, May 30, 1983. Day 2. Pages 330-402 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 38th Convention. Tuesday, May 31, 1983. Day 3. Pages 403-549 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- 38th Convention. Tuesday, May 31, 1983. Day 3. Pages 550-666A (Box 1, Folder 21)
- 38th Convention. Wednesday, June 1, 1983. Day 4. Pages 667-805 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 38th Convention. Wednesday, June 1, 1983. Day 4. Pages 806-969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 38th Convention. Thursday, June 2, 1983. Day 5. Pages 970-1112 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 38th Convention. Thursday, June 2, 1983. Day 5. Pages 1113-1264 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Melman, David. Memorandum. Convention Cards. June 18, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Opening. Friday, May 30, 9 AM, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 6)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Morning. Monday, June [2], [1986] (Box 2, Folder 7)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Sen. Hollings. Monday, June 2, 9 AM, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 8)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Lance Kirkland. Monday, June 2, 11 AM, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 9)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Afternoon. Monday, June 2, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 10)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Morning. Tuesday, June 3, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 11)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. ILG Birthday. Morning. Tuesday, June 3, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 12)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Emma Mashinini. Tuesday, June 3, 11:30 AM, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 13)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Afternoon. Tuesday, June 3, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 14)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Imports Video, (Imports Committee). Afternoon. Tuesday, June 3, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 15)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Executive V.P., Irwin Solomon. Afternoon. Tuesday, June 3, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 16)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Shirley Carr. Tuesday, June 3, 3 PM, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 17)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Morning. Wednesday, June 4, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 18)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Statue of Liberty. (Resolutions Report). Morning. Wednesday, June 4, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 19)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Governor Kunin. Wednesday, June 4, 10 AM, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 20)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Claude Pepper. Wednesday, June 4, 10:45 AM, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 21)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Afternoon. Wednesday, June 4, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 22)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Retiree Presentation. Afternoon. Wednesday, June 4, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 23)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Morning. Thursday, June 5, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 24)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Triangle Video, (Resolutions Committee). Morning. Thursday, June 5, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 25)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Afternoon. Thursday, June 5, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 26)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. SCC Tribute. Afternoon. Thursday, June 5, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 27)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Elections. Friday, June 6, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 28)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Appeals, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 29)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Credentials, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 30)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Education, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 31)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Finance, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 32)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. GST Mazur Financial Report, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 33)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Imports, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 34)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. ILGWU Institutions and Welfare, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 35)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. International Affairs, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 36)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Law, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 37)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Offices Report, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 38)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Organization, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 39)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Resolution, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 40)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Rules, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 41)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Social and Labor Legislation, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 42)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Union Label, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 43)
- [39th Convention]. Convention Cards. Work Standards, [1986] (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Lazar, Robert. Memorandum. Convention Proceedings. November 13, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- 39th Convention. Friday Morning Session. May 30, 1986. Volume I, Pages 1-91 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- 39th Convention. Monday Morning Session. June 2, 1986. Volume I, Pages 92-209 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- 39th Convention. Monday Afternoon Session. June 2, 1986. Volume I, Pages 210-280 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- 39th Convention. Tuesday Morning Session. June 3, 1986. Volume I, Pages 281-392 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- 39th Convention. Tuesday Afternoon Session. June 3, 1986. Volume I, Pages 393-474 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- 39th Convention. Wednesday Morning Session. June 4, 1986. Volume II, Pages 475-587 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- 39th Convention. Wednesday Afternoon Session. June 4, 1986. Volume II, Pages 588-685 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- 39th Convention. Thursday Morning Session. June 5, 1986. Volume II, Pages 686-783 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- 39th Convention. Thursday Afternoon Session. June 5, 1986. Volume II, Pages 784-895 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- 39th Convention. Friday Morning Session. June 6, 1986. Volume II, Pages 896-978 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- [39th Convention]. Mike Labels 1 and 2 [Folder 1 of 2], [1986] (Box 2, Folder 56)
- [39th Convention]. Mike Labels 1 and 2 [Folder 2 of 2], [1986] (Box 2, Folder 57)
- [39th Convention]. Mike Labels 3 and 4 [Folder 1 of 2], [1986] (Box 3, Folder 1)
- [39th Convention]. Mike Labels 3 and 4 [Folder 2 of 2], [1986] (Box 3, Folder 2)
- [39th Convention]. Mike Labels 5 and 6 [Folder 1 of 2], [1986] (Box 3, Folder 3)
- [39th Convention]. Mike Labels 5 and 6 [Folder 2 of 2], [1986] (Box 3, Folder 4)
- 40th Convention. Friday Session. June 2, 1989. Pages 2-103 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- 40th Convention. Monday Morning Session. June 5, 1989. Pages 104-183 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 40th Convention. Monday Morning Session. June 5, 1989. Pages 184-240 Missing (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 40th Convention. Monday Afternoon Session. June 5, 1989. Pages 241-423 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- 40th Convention. Tuesday Session. June 6, 1989. Pages 424-589 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- 40th Convention. Wednesday Morning Session. June 7, 1989. Pages 590-741 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 40th Convention. Wednesday Afternoon Session. June 7, 1989. Pages 742-895 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- 40th Convention. Thursday Morning Session. June 8, 1989. Pages 896-1014 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- 40th Convention. Thursday Afternoon Session. June 8, 1989. Pages 1015-1172 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- 40th Convention. Friday Session. June 9, 1989. Pages 1173-1275 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- 41st Convention. Proceedings, Days 1-6, June 12-19, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)